A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Program Strategy records FA1389
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Program Strategy records
1974-1996
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA1389
3.87 Cubic Feet
Scope and Contents
The collection contains Office of Communications officers' files, supervising secretaries' meeting notes and memoranda, memoranda from the Ford Foundation president to the trustees, files related to the Foundation's office automation process, and reports to the trustees, primarily from the 1990s. "Program Strategy" is a Ford Foundation term for material that pertains to materials that move the Foundation forward and guide decision-making practices.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Ford Foundation in 2017 and 2018 and ingested by RAC as Accessions 2017:080 and 2018:087.
Arrangement
Arranged as received from the Ford Foundation in 2017 and 2018.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas.
During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Ford Foundation; Communications; Office management
- Chile Office Booklet/Brochure, 1992 August-September (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Statement of Franklin A. Thomas before the U.S. Senate Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs, 1992 September 17 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Franklin Thomas Testimony Before the Senate Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs, 1992 September 17; VHS; Sound, Color, 169 minutes (Box 6, Tape AV 11192)
    Related Materials
    Transcription available in original folder location.
    Conditions Governing Access
    Access copy available.
    Scope and Contents
    Ford Foundation President Franklin Thomas testifies before the Senate Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs on the subject of Federal Government support for urban aid. Also testifying are executives from other philanthropic organizations like the Rockefeller Foundation and the Mott Foundation. Senator Donald Riegle of Michigan chairs the Senate Committee. Thomas' statement begins around the 1:32:55 time mark. He discusses a framework for including the experiences and opinions of the people living in cities to address the problems many American urban areas face.
    Testimony was delivered on September 17, 1992, and the recording aired on C-SPAN 2 on September 20, 1992 at 1:25 p.m.
    The recording of the hearing ends around the 2:35:00 time mark.
  - WPF 5.0 The Ford Foundation, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
- Press Release: Joan R. Dassin Named Director of Latin American and Caribbean Programs, 1992 September 28 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Untitled, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Julio C. Nunez - Office of Communications - Faxes and Correspondence, 1992 January-August (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Tina Rosenberg - Consultant Trip to Brazil, 1992 April (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Julio C. Nunez - Misc. Memos, 1992 April-June (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Current Business - Franklin Thomas - International Institute for Strategic Studies (IISS) Meeting, Berlin, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Current Business - Franklin Thomas' Rio Speech, 1992 June (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Rio Speech 7536T, 1992 June 22 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Current Business - Press Release Draft - Joan R. Dassin, 1992 June (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Current Business - First Report on Staff Responses to the Los Angeles Disturbances, 1992 June 23 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Current Business - Incoming Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1992 April-July (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Memos and correspondence regarding the 1992 Innovations Program, press release materials, Tina Rosemberg's Sao Paulo visit, US Mexico Journalist Exhange, Working Paper from The Helen Kellogg Institute for International Studies, University of Notre Dame, job opportunities, summer interns, etc.
- Current Business - Faxed Sheets, 1992 April (Box 1, Folder 12)
  One facsimile cover page addressed to Kristin Goss, Chronicle of Philanthropy from Lloyd Garrison, Office of Communications
- Current Business - PBS BBC Taping Session - Ford Building, 1992 April (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Current Business - Graphics Center Request Proposal, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Current Business - Malone Gill Productions, Ltd - Filming Nature Perfected, 1992 June-July (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Supervising Secretaries' Meetings, 1989 February-1996 March (Box 2, Folder 16-20)
- Decision to Continue Existence, 1974-1982 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  Memos to the Trustees from McGeorge Bundy and Franklin A. Thomas; Ford Foundation Annual Report 1974; Retrenchment of Management Costs: Progress Report II; Preliminary Recommendations on the Foundation's Future Directions
- Office Automation Task Force (OATF) - Yankee Group, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 22-23)
- Office Automation Task Force (OATF), 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 24-28, Box 4, Folder 29)
- International Institute of Strategic Studies, Alastair Buchan Memorial Lecture - Role of the United Nations in Maintaining and Improving International Security, 1986 March 20 (Box 5, Folder 30)
- An Overview of the Dispute Resolution Field, A Report to the Ford Foundation - Christine B. Harrington, 1986 May (Box 5, Folder 31)
- Status Report on Foundation Work in Dispute Resolution - For Discussion at the December 1985 Trustees' Meeting, 1985 December (Box 5, Folder 32)
- Corporate Involvement Initiative: A Progress Report Prepared for the Meeting of the Committee on Program-Related Investments, 1995 December (Box 5, Folder 33)
- Report on Project on the Future and the Welfare State, 1984 June 8 (Box 5, Folder 34)
- Human Rights and Social Justice Program (US International Affairs Program and Developing Countries Program) FY 1982-FY 1986 Grants List - Arranged Alphabetically, 1982-1986 (Box 5, Folder 35)
- International Affairs Program (US International Affairs Program and Developing Countries Program) International Refugee and Migration Policy FY 1982-FY 1986 Grant List - Arranged by Sub-Topics, 1982-1986 (Box 5, Folder 36)
- Refugees and Migrants: Problems and Program Responses - Update of June 1983 Trustees' Information Paper, 1983 June (Box 5, Folder 37)
- Terrorism: Its Political Uses and Abuses, Gary G. Sick, undated (Box 5, Folder 38)
- Encouraging Stability, Peace and Justice in the International Order - Volume I (2 copies), 1987 June (Box 5, Folder 39-40)
- Encouraging Stability, Peace and Justice in the International Order - Volume II and Appendices (2 copies), 1987 June (Box 5, Folder 41-42)
- Discussion Paper: Welfare and Teenage Pregnancy Program, For the June 1984 Meeting of the Ford Foundation Board of Trustees, 1984 June (Box 5, Folder 43)
- Discussion Paper: Improving American Governance: Problems and Strategies, For Discussion at the June 1985 Trustees' Meeting, 1985 June (Box 5, Folder 44)
- The Role of New Immigrants in Rejuvenating New York's Neighborhoods, Sunset Park: A Case Study (Draft), 1987 December (Box 6, Folder 45)
- Program-Related Investments: Program Review, 1984 June (Box 6, Folder 46)
- Discussion Paper: Overview of Program - Mexico and Central America, For Discussion at the March 1992 Trustees' Meeting, 1992 March (Box 6, Folder 47)
- Overview: Selected Social Welfare Reports, 1987 January (Box 6, Folder 48)
- The Ford Foundation International Division, Summary Tables FY 1980 and Comparisons with Earlier Years, 1981 May 22 (Box 6, Folder 49)
- Overview of Program: South Africa and Namibia, Board of Trustees Meeting, 1990 June 27 (Box 6, Folder 50)
- The Ford Foundation, International Division, Summary Tables FY 1977 and Earlier Years, 1978 March 16 (Box 6, Folder 51)
- Trustees' Visit to Urban Poverty Programs for Youth Work, Service and Learning, 1985 June 26 (Box 6, Folder 52)
- FY 1991 Program Review - Israel, 1991 April (Box 6, Folder 53)
- FY 1991 Program Review - South Africa and Namibia, 1991 April (Box 6, Folder 54)
- Discussion Paper: Reproductive Health and Population Program, A Progress Report, For Discussion at the September 1992 Trustees' Meeting, 1990-1992 (Box 6, Folder 55)
- Program-Related Investments, Review Paper, For Discussion at the December 1993 Meeting of the PRI Special Committee of the Trustees, 1993 December (Box 6, Folder 56)
- Background Memoranda for Trustee Discussion of Program Priorities for the FY 1994 and FY 1995 Biennium, 1993 March (Box 6, Folder 57)
- Discussion Paper: The Urban Poverty Program in the United States, For Discussion at the September 1995 Meeting of the Urban and Rural Poverty Committee, 1995 September (Box 7, Folder 58)
- Sexuality and Reproductive Health: Reproductive Health and Population Program: A Progress Report, For Discussion at the December 1994 Meeting of the Board of Trustees, 1994 December (Box 7, Folder 59)
- The Ford Foundation: The Formative Years, William Greenleaf (2 folders), undated (Box 7, Folder 60-61)
- The Ford Foundation: The Formative Years, William Greenleaf (with sticky note edits) (2 folders), undated (Box 7, Folder 62-63)
- International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research, Bangladesh (ICDDR,B): History of Interim International Committee Meetings and Other Developments (2 folders), 1978 (Box 7, Folder 64)